CHAPTER 3

Social Justice:
An Ambedkarian Perspective

INTRODUCTION

This chapter conceptualizes the idea of ‘social justice’ in Ambedkar’s thought. Taking reference from Plato and Rawls, the chapter evolves the idea of social justice with the help of Ambedkar’s writings and speeches published posthumously by the Maharashtra government. In doing so, it has identified five basic principles of ‘social justice’ in the social thought of Ambedkar. These are—first related to the relationship between the individual and society, and second the establishment of a just social order. According to Ambedkar, a just social order can only be developed on the basis of equality, liberty, and fraternity. That means his scheme of social justice includes the establishment of a just social order, which should be based on equality, liberty, and fraternity, which he has drawn from his master, the Buddha.

The third principle of social justice in Ambedkar’s thought is associated with the fact that democracy in a society should not be restricted only to political spheres. In other words, a democracy will not be a true democracy—if individuals have only political equality. Political equality here means that they all can cast their votes freely. No doubt, in such a condition, according to him, there will be the principle of ‘one man one vote, one vote one value’ in politics. However, a democracy will be true democracy only when equality is also extended in social and economic spheres along with the political sphere. Hence, we can argue that the establishment of a true democracy with social, economic and political equality is the third principle of social justice in Ambedkar’s thought.

The fourth principle of Ambedkar’s scheme of social justice includes its dispensation via constitutional means. He argued that if we want to strengthen democracy, then we should not adopt extra-constitutional mechanisms; instead, we should be steadfast in adherence to constitutional means for achieving our social and economic objectives. If we have constitutional means to meet our social, economic and political demand, we should not, as Ambedkar used to say, resort to unconstitutional measures like satyagraha (civil disobedience movements).

The fifth principle of social justice in Ambedkar’s thought is dismantling the monopoly of the so-called ‘upper castes’. In this regard, he believes that social justice cannot be enforced on its own; rather, it has to be made effective. And it can be made effective, according to Ambedkar, if and only if the Civil Administration of that society is not against the emergence of an egalitarian social order. In his vision, Indian Civil Services have been biased towards the old hierarchical social order. That is why he emphasized that if we have to make social justice effective, then we have to make our bureaucracy more representative.

In the following pages, we will elaborate on these points in detail.

THE CONCEPT OF SOCIAL JUSTICE

To begin with, Plato defined social justice as,

the principle of a society consisting of different types of men . . . who have combined the impulse of their need for one another and their concentration on their combination in one society and their concentration on their separate functions have made a whole, which is perfect because it is the product of the image of the whole of the human mind (Republic 368d quoted in Mohapatra 1999).

In modern times the term social justice was first used in 1840 by a Sicilian priest, Luigi Taparelli d’Azeglio. However, Antonio Rasmini Serbasti gave the term prominence in his work, La Constitutione Civile Secodo La Giurtizia Sociale, in the year 1848 (Noval 2000: 11 as quoted in Yadav 2006).

Further, in a series of articles beginning with Justice as Fairness, Rawls propounded his theory of justice. His theory is considered a contractual theory of justice as it applies to institutions and practices, and is based on the notions of fairness and reciprocity. Rawls believed that his theory of justice was an improvement over utilitarian accounts of justice as maximum welfare. Where the utilitarian theory of justice treats society as a collective person and aims at maximizing its satisfaction without regard for the gains and losses of actual persons, Rawls’s conception treats society distributively, taking into account the autonomy and right to the satisfaction of each member. Rawls developed the following principles of justice:

1. Each person is to have an equal right to have the most extensive basic liberty compatible with a similar liberty for others.

2a. Social and economic inequities are arbitrary unless they are reasonably expected to be to the advantage of the representative man in each income class.

2b. Inequalities are to attach to positions and offices equally open to all. (Choptiany 1973: 146)

Therefore, while conceptualizing the theory of justice, according to Rawls,

. . . the principles . . . would be chosen at least in preference to other traditional alternatives, by rational persons, in an original position of equality as their common conception of justice’. (ibid)

Similarly, taking a leaf from Rawls’s theory of social justice, Beteille (2005: 417) argues, ‘. . . the fundamental issue in distributive justice is equality; a more equal or at least a less unequal distribution of the benefits and of social cooperation.’ He further opines that

In that sense, distributive justice to go beyond equality in the purely formal sense: equality before the law, seeks to go beyond equality in the purely formal sense: equality before the law, the equal protection of the laws, or even formal equality of opportunity. Its central concern is, in the language of Rawls, ‘to address the bias of contingencies in the direction of equality’. . . . Any attempt to promote distributive justice must begin with a consideration of the existing inequalities in society. . . . It is essential to keep in sight both inequalities between individuals and disparities. Disparities between groups have been historically of great significance in Indian society.

Plato’s and Rawls’s concept of social justice would mean giving every man his due. However, a universal theory of social justice has not evolved either in the Western liberal philosophy or in the socialist and communist doctrine yet. Certain basic ingredients of the concept of social justice have already been projected through the international human rights document and the Indian constitution. Accordingly, the basic aim of social justice is to remove the imbalances in the social, political, and economic life of the people to create a just society. Regarding culture-specificity, the term social justice has a different meaning in Indian society. It means dispensing justice to those to whom it has been systematically denied in the past, to those historically subjected to social wrongs because of an established social structure.

SOCIAL JUSTICE IN AMBEDKAR’S WRITINGS

It is a fact that Ambedkar did not propound any specific definition or theory of ‘Social Justice’ per se. However, in the light of principles enshrined in the theories of ‘social justice’, as propounded by Plato and Rawls, one could infer basic cultural and structural principles of social justice embodied in the thoughts of Ambedkar. These thoughts are eloquently portrayed in his writings and speeches published posthumously. Based on these, we can easily argue that Ambedkar has mentioned multiple principles for establishing an open and just social order, in general and Indian society, in particular. Therefore, with the help of these characteristics, we can carve out a social justice theory. If we succeed in doing that, then we can refer to it as Ambedkar’s theory of social justice. Drawing upon the principles he has laid down in his writings and speeches through which social justice can be ensured to the masses, we can identify and underline five fundamental principles (Kumar 2008: 107):

1. Establishing a society where an individual becomes the means of all social purposes.

2. Establishment of society based on equality, liberty and fraternity.

3. Establishing a political, economic and social democracy.

4. Establishing a democracy through constitutional measures.

5. Establishing a democracy by breaking the monopoly of upper strata on political power.

RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN
INDIVIDUAL AND SOCIETY

To achieve the goals mentioned above, he launched the long, arduous, multilayered movement specifically for the most neglected and marginalized groups of the Hindu society—the Dalits. Further, he also laid the foundation for disseminating social justice for every section of Indian society. Going by the principles of Ambedkar’s theory of social justice, Ambedkar believed that social justice can be dispensed in a free social order in which an individual is an end in itself. Similarly, terms of associated lives between members of society must be regarded as founded on liberty, equality, and fraternity. In a way, these principles of social justice are similar to those of social justice, as mentioned in Rawls’s theory. Let us look at these principles in operation.

Arguing a case for open social order in his writings, Ambedkar emphasized that, generally, there are two fundamentals and essentials of free social order. He states,

The first is that the individual is an end himself, and that the aim and object of society is the growth of the individual and the development of his personality. Society is not above the individual; if the individual has to subordinate himself to society, it is because such subordination is for his betterment and only to the extent necessary (Ambedkar 1987(c): 95).

With this aim, Ambedkar rejected the village as a unit of governance and adopted the individual as its unit. He vehemently criticized the part played by village communities in history and congratulated the Drafting Committee for accepting individuals as the unit of governance (Ambedkar 1994: 61-2). Ambedkar had argued for the individual as the end itself as he was fully aware of the fact that

The Hindu social order does not recognize the individual as a centre of social purpose. . . . The Hindu social order is based principally on a class or varna and not on individuals. . . . The unit of Hindu society is not the individual Brahmin or the individual Kshatriya. . . . Even the family is not regarded by the Hindu social order as the unit of society except for the purposes of marriage and inheritance. . . . In the Hindu social order, there is no room for individual merit and no consideration of individual justice (Ambedkar 1987(c): 99).

SOCIAL JUSTICE: EQUALITY, LIBERTY,
AND FRATERNITY

Ambedkar has always advocated for establishing a society based on the principles of liberty, fraternity, and equality. This has to be for every individual. It may be so because he understood that social justice can be ensured to the members of the society only if the society is based on equality, liberty and fraternity. This is quite similar to the argument given by Plato, who opines that social justice is the principle in which individuals combine their efforts for others. This can happen when men are treated as equals. However, one is forced to argue that this can happen only when there is fraternity in society. For this, society has to be established on the basis of the three principles, that is ‘liberty, equality and fraternity’. In this context, let us see what Ambedkar says. Explaining his notion of an ideal society, Ambedkar emphasized, ‘. . . my ideal would be a society based on Liberty, Equality and Fraternity’ (Ambedkar 1979: 57).

Delineating the characteristics of fraternity, he opined,

An ideal society should be mobile, full of channels for conveying a change taking place in one part to another. In an ideal society, many interests should be consciously communicated and shared. There should be varied and free points and contacts with other modes and associations. In other words, there must be social endosmosis. This is a fraternity, which is only another name for democracy. Democracy is not merely a form of government. It is a primary mode of associated living, of conjoint communicated experience. It is essentially an attitude of respect and reverence towards followers (ibid).

Further, Ambedkar explains the notion and importance of liberty. In his words,

Few object to liberty in the sense of a right to free movement. There is no problem with liberty in the sense of the right to property, tools and materials as being necessary for earning a living, to keep the body in due state of health. Why not allow liberty to benefit by an effective and competent use of a person’s power? However, the problem is that people who support liberty in the sense of right to life, limb and property would not readily consent to liberty if it involves the liberty to choose one’s profession (Ambedkar 1979: 57).

Ambedkar further argues that,

. . . to object to the liberty to choose a profession is to perpetuate slavery. For slavery does not merely mean a legalize form of subjection. It means a state of society in which some men are forced to accept other occupations which control their conduct. This condition is found even where there is no slavery in the legal sense. For instance, it is found in the society where caste system is prevalent because some persons are compelled to carry on certain prescribed calling which are not of their choice.

This brings us the notion of equality as deliberated by Ambedkar. According to him,

. . . The objection to equality may be sound and one may have to admit that all men are not equal. Equality may be a fiction but nonetheless accept it as the governing principle. A man’s power is dependent upon (1) physical heredity (2) social inheritance or endowment in the form of parental care, education, accumulation of scientific knowledge, everything which enables him to be more efficient than the savage, and finally, (3) on his own efforts. In all these three aspects men are undoubtly unequal. But the question is, shall we treat them as unequal because they are unequal? . . . From the point of view of the individualist, it may be just to treat men unequally so far, their efforts are unequal. It may be desirable to give as much as incentives as possible to the full development of every one’s powers. But what would happen if men were treated unequally as they are, in the first two respects? It is obvious that those individuals also in whose favor there is birth, education, family name, business connection and inherited wealth would be selected in the race. But selection under such circumstances would not be a selection of the abled. It would be the selection of the privileged. The reason, therefore, which forces that in the third respect we should treat men unequally demands, that in the first two respects we should treat men as equally as possible (Ibid.: 58).

In this context Ambedkar also explains why we cannot run away from equality. According to him,

. . . it can be urged that if it is good for the social body to get the most out and its members, it can get most out of them only by making them equal as far as possible at the very start of the race. That is one reason why we cannot escape equality. There is a second reason for accepting equality. A statesman is concerned with the vast majority of people. He has neither the time nor the knowledge to draw fine distinctions and to treat each equally, i.e., according to need or according to capacity. However desirable or reasonable and equitable treatment of men may be, humanity is not capable of assortment and classification. The statesmen, therefore, must follow some rough and ready rule and that ready and rough rule is to treat all men alike and not because they are alike but because classification and assortment are impossible. The doctrine of equality is glaringly fallacious but taking all in all, it is the only way a statesmen can proceed in politics which is a severely practicable affair, and which demands a severely practical test (Ambedkar 1979: 57-8).

ESTABLISHING DEMOCRACY POLITICAL,
ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL

Here, it is interesting to note that Ambedkar’s principles of social justice were not only philosophical and theoretical propositions rather, but he also tried to give them practical shape as well. That is why, after India’s political independence, for dispensing social justice in the wake of emerging democracy in a hierarchically arranged society, Ambedkar discussed the ways and means to operationalize the principles of equality, liberty, and fraternity, which were considered to be cardinal principles of any democracy. In this regard, he argued in the constituent assembly that ‘We must . . . not . . . be content with mere political democracy. We must make sure our political democracy is a social democracy as well’ (Ambedkar 1994: 1216).

In the same vein, Ambedkar went on to define social democracy as well. In his own words,

What does social democracy mean? It means a way of life that recognizes liberty, equality, and fraternity as the principles of life. These principles of liberty, equality and fraternity should not be treated as separate items of trinity (Ambedkar 1994: 1216).

Another significant contribution of Ambedkar in the process of establishing a social democracy is his explanation of the nature of three cardinal principles of democracy, i.e., liberty, quality, and fraternity. He opined,

They form a union of trinity, in the sense that to divorce one from the other is to defeat the very purpose of democracy. Liberty cannot be divorced from equality; equality cannot be divorced from liberty. Nor can liberty and equality be divorced from fraternity.

Without equality, liberty would produce the supremacy of the few over many. Equality without freedom would kill individual initiative. Without fraternity, liberty and equality could not become a natural course of things. . . . We must begin by acknowledging the fact that there is a complete absence of two things in Indian society. One of these is equality. On the social plane, we have in India a society based on the principle of graded inequality, which means the elevation of some and the degradation of others. On the economic plane, we have a society in which there are some, who have immense wealth as against many, who live in abject poverty (Ambedkar 1994: 1216).

Finally, he cautioned the Indians on how to eradicate the conditions of persisting inequality and create cordial conditions about emerging equality, taking the help of social justice. In his own words,

On the 26 January 1950, we are going to enter into a life of contradictions. In politics, we will have equality, and in socio-economic life, we will have inequality. In politics, we will recognize the principle of one man one vote, and one vote one value. In our social and economic life, we shall, because of our social and economic structure, continue to live this life of contradiction. How long shall we continue to live this life of contradictions? If we continue to deny it for long, we will do so only by putting our political democracy in peril. We must remove this contradiction at the earliest possible moment, or else those who suffer from inequality will blow up the structure of political democracy. . . . The second thing we want is recognition of the principle of fraternity. What does fraternity mean? Fraternity means a sense of common brotherhood of Indians—If Indians being one people. It is the principle that gives unity and solidarity to social life. It is a difficult thing to achieve (Ambedkar 1994: 1216-17).

DEMOCRACY THROUGH
CONSTITUTIONAL MEASURES

Although initially, Ambedkar was skeptical of ensuring justice to the erstwhile excluded communities through bureaucracy, however, later on, he preferred the same by asking Dalits to claim their share in it. Going by the then-existing Hindu social order, Ambedkar expressed his anguish on the failure of delivery of justice to the excluded groups like the ex-untouchables. That is why he once opined,

It might have been brought that the principle of equal justice would strike a death blow to the established order. As a matter of fact, far from suffering any damage, the established order has continued to operate in spite of it. It might be asked why the principle of equal justice has failed to have its effect. The answer to this is simple. To enunciate the principle of justice is one thing. To make it effective is another thing. Whether the principle of equal justice is effective or not must necessarily depend upon the nature and character of the civil services, which must be left to administer the principle. If the civil services are, by reason of their class bias, the friend of the established order and the enemy of the new order; the new order can never come into being.

That civil service in tune with the new order was essential for the success of the new order was recognized by Marx in 1871 in the formation of the Paris Commune and adopted by Lenin in the constitution of Soviet communism. Fortunately, the British government never cared about the personnel of the Civil Services. Indeed, it opened the gates of the administration to those classes who believed in the old established order of the Hindus in which the principle of equality had no place. As a result of this fact, India has been ruled by the British but administered by the Hindus’ (Ambedkar 1989(a): 104).

Further, he argued,

The police and the Magistrate are sometimes corrupt. If they were only corrupt, perhaps things would not be so bad because an officer who is corrupt is open to purchase by either party. But the misfortune is that the police and magistrate are often more partial than corrupt. It is this partiality to the Hindus and his antipathy to the untouchables, which results in the denial of protection and justice to the untouchables (Ambedkar 1989(a): 105-6).

However, as time passed by, Ambedkar gradually became aware that social justice can be delivered through the government machinery and through constitutional means and therefore, Dalits have to be part of it. In this context, he wrote,

The power to administer law is not less important than the power to make laws. And the spirit of the legislators may easily be violated if not nullified by the machinery of the administrators. This is not the only reason why the depressed classes should show special concern for securing power of control over administration. Often-times, under pressure of work or under difficult circumstances, one has to leave a good deal of discretionary power in the hands of the heads of the administrative departments. The welfare of the people must greatly depend on how impartially this discretionary power is exercised in a country like India, where the public service is exclusively manned by people of one community; there is a great danger of this vast discretionary power being used for the personal aggrandizement of a class. The best antidote against it is to insist on a proper admixture of caste and creeds, including the depressed classes, and there will be no difficulty in guaranteeing this safeguard to us by a clause in the constitution. Such protection you could have dispensed with if there was any chance of the depressed classes being represented in the future cabinets of the country. But there is not the remotest chance of this because the depressed classes will always remain in the minority. This makes it all the more necessary to insist upon such a guarantee (Ambedkar, 2003: 37).

Moreover, Ambedkar cautioned people that

If we wish to maintain democracy not merely in form, but also in fact, . . . we must hold fast to constitutional methods of achieving our social and economic objectives. It means we must abandon the bloody methods of revolution. It means that we must abandon the method of civil disobedience, non-cooperation, and satyagraha. When there was no way left for constitutional methods to achieve economic and social objectives, there was a great deal of justification for unconstitutional methods. But where constitutional methods are open, there can be no justification for these unconstitutional methods. These methods are nothing but the grammar of anarchy, and the sooner they are abandoned, the better for us (Ambedkar 1994: 1215).

BREAKING THE MONOPOLY
OF UPPER STRATA

Ambedkar was also a proponent of freedom of the individual as well. Furthermore, even for the healthy future of the emerging Indian democracy, he wanted to strengthen social and economic equality along with political one. According to him, one of the ways to deliver social justice to the individual was by breaking the monopoly of the upper strata. Ambedkar (1994: 1218) in this regard, opined,

. . . there can be no gainsaying that political power in this country has too long been the monopoly of a few. This monopoly has not merely deprived them of their chance of betterment; it has sapped them of what may be called the significance of life. These downtrodden classes are tired of being governed. They are impatient to govern themselves. This urge for self-realization in the downtrodden classes must not be allowed into a class struggle or class war. It would lead to a division of the House. That would be a day of disaster. For, as has been well said by Abraham Lincoln, a house divided against itself cannot stand very long. Therefore, the sooner the room is made for the realization of their aspiration, the better for the few, the better for the country, and the better for the maintenance of its structure. This can only be done by the establishment of equality and fraternity in all spheres of life. People are fast changing. . . . They are getting tired of the government by the people. They are prepared to have a government for the people. . . . If we wish to preserve the constitution in which we have sought to enshrine the principle of government of the people, for the people, and by the people, let us resolve not to be tardy in the recognition of the evils that lie across our path and which induce people to prefer government for the people to government by the people, nor to be weak in our initiative to remove them.

CONCLUSION

In conclusion we can argue that social justice generally deals with allocating scarce resources to a population. It is based on the idea of due process, impartiality, and distribution according to appropriate criteria (Marshal 1998: 333). We have also seen that the social justice debate starts with Plato and gets established with John Rawls’s theory of the ‘difference principle’. According to this principle, ‘. . . inequalities in the distribution of scarce goods are justified only if they serve to increase the advantage of the least favored groups of society’ (ibid: 334). Taking clues from these basic elements of social justice from Plato and Rawls, this chapter has tried to search for these elements in the thoughts of Ambedkar found in his writings and speeches. These five characteristics of Ambedkar’s social justice theory identified in this chapter, are one—individuals should be developed as free and independent agents, two—society should be based on equality, liberty, and fraternity; third—establishment of true democracy based on social, economic and political equality; fourth—establishing democracy through constitutional measures, and fifth—breaking the monopoly of the so-called upper-strata on political power.

It becomes clear that by propounding the principles above of social justice, Ambedkar wanted to deconstruct the existing socio-political structure of Indian society so that social justice can be effectively ensured to the masses. It can be argued that he must have propounded these principles because he was aware of the nature of Indian society in which a considerable percentage of the population has been cumulatively excluded from rights—social, economic, political, educational, religious, and even right to natural resources. It is interesting that Ambedkar did not evolve these aforesaid principles of social justice only as philosophical and theoretical prepositions. Instead, he backed and substantiated these principles with specific constitutional provisions. He did not believe that the political leaders or general masses would be interested in dispensing social justice to the excluded in the coming days. Hence, he enshrined them in the Constitution of India with their minutest of details, so that the excluded and depressed should be ensured of their rights, privileges, and entitlements as the citizens of the nation. The debate on social justice of this chapter will be elaborated further in the next chapter, that is, Ambedkar ideas of nation and nation building.

REFERENCES

Ambedkar, B.R., 1979, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 1, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1987(c), Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 3, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1989(a), Untouchables or the Children of Indian’s Ghetto and other Essays on Untouchables and Untouchability: Social-Political-Religious in Babasaheb Ambedkar Writing and Speeches, vol. 5, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1994, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 13, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 2003, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 17 (part three). Education Department, Government of Maharashtra.

Béteille, Andre, 2005, ‘Distributive Justice and Institutional Well-Being’ in Dipankar Gupta (ed.) Anti-Utopia: Essential Writings of Andre Béteille, Oxford University Press, New Delhi.

Choptiany, Leonard, 1973, ‘A Critique of John Rawls’s Principles of Justice’, Ethics, vol. 83, no. 2 (January) (pp.146-50), The University Press Chicago, Chicago.

Kumar, Vivek, 2008, ‘Babasaheb Ambedkar: Conceptualization and Operationalization of Social Justice’, in P.G. Jogdand et al. Globalization and Social Justice: Perspective, Challenges and Praxis, Rawat Publications, Delhi.

Marshall, Gorden, 1998, Oxford Dictionary of Sociology, Oxford University Press, New Delhi.

Mohapatra, P.K., Social Justice: A Philosophical Perspective, D.K. Printers, New Delhi.

Yadav, Sushma, 2006, Social Justice: Ambedkar’s Vision, Dr. Ambedkar Studies, Department of Sociology, Jammu University of Jammu, Jammu & Kashmir.